Osama Shahid . Jarvis Consulting

I graduated with a Bachelor's in Chemistry from McMaster University, but have always had a keen interest in technology. I worked as a junior Software Developer at Select Vantage shortly afterward, creating python scripts and trading tools to be used in equity markets. I am currently finishing up my Master's degree in Computer Science and have joined Jarvis alongside. Since then, I have been collaborating with my team members in an Agile/Scrum environment to create backend applications. With that, I have acquired and solidified my knowledge by working on multiple projects, specifically with technologies such as Linux/Bash, RDMS/PostgresSQL, Dockers, Maven, etc. I am passionate about solving real-world problems and want to move my career forward as a Software Developer.

Skills

Proficient: Java/Maven, Python, Linux/Bash, RDBMS/SQL, NoSQL/MongoDB, Agile/Scrum, Git

Competent: JavaScript, React, Nodejs, HTML/CSS, GitFlow, Docker

Familiar: GCP, C/C++, Neo4j, AWS, Springboot

Jarvis Projects

Project source code: https://github.com/jarviscanada/jarvis_data_eng_demo_OsamaShahid

Cluster Monitor [GitHub]: Implemented a clustering monitoring program that automates the collects hardware and CPU usage information from the Linux servers using Bash scripts and Crontab. The data was stored in a PostgreSQL database that was initialized using Dockers. It was later than queried to perform analytics on overall usage and identify downtimes during high server usage. We utilized Git as a version control tool and GitFlow branching strategy.

Core Java Apps [GitHub]:

- Twitter App: A command-line application that allows users to create, show and delete tweets. This was created using Java/Maven and Spring for dependency management. Also performed integration and unit testing utilizing Mockito framework. Finally built an image using dockers and uploaded it to the docker hub.
- JDBC App: Implemented JDBC to connect to a Postgres database and execute CRUD operation following the Data Access Object (DAO) design pattern.
- Grep App: Created application to mimic Linux grep command and utilized stream APIs to optimize efficiency. This app was then packaged using Maven and was Dockerized by building an image and uploading it to the docker hub.

Highlighted Projects

Fifa Dashboard [GitHub]: Created this dashboard to search for player and match statistics that can potentially be used for sports betting. The frontend application was built using React and the backend using Nodejs. The dataset was stored using a MySQL database hosted on AWS-RDS. The dataset was normalized to the 3rd-normal form and the query times were optimized using indexing.

Social Media Application [GitHub]: The application allows users to log in/signup, post threads, and interact with other users using the app. This frontend was created using React/Redux and Nodejs for the backend. Also, Firebase was utilized for authentication and database storage.

Professional Experiences

Software Developer, Jarvis (2021-present): Worked in an Agile/Scrum environment to implement multiple projects using Linux/Bash, Java, Docker, SQL, etc. Conducted daily scrum meetings and bi-weekly retro meetings.

Software Developer, Select Vantage Inc. (2019-2020): Created Python tools and programs to help retrieve live trading information to help improve trading efficiency. Utilized Python modules for data processing/analysis and implemented scripts to reduce time sorting data.

Research Assistant, McMaster University (2017 - 2019): Utilized Python libraries for data analysis and visualizations instead of using manual techniques like excel. Created and led a team project regarding the exploration of cholesterol-embedded lipid systems in membranes studying lysis analytics (2nd Author Publication).

Education

University of Pennsylvania (2020-Present), Master's of Computer Science, School of Engineering and Applied Sciences

McMaster University (2015-2019), Bachelors of Science, Chemistry and Chemical Biology

Miscellaneous

- Soccer and Basketball
- Competitive gaming
- Radio Co-Host